Guide to the Revolutionary Workers League papers, 1935-1945
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Revolutionary Workers League papers 1935-1945
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Revolutionary Workers League.
0.5 linear feet Extent: 148 Items
The Revolutionary Workers League (RWL) was a radical left group in the United States active from 1935 until about 1947. The League was formed by Hugo Oehler in November 1935 following a split from the Workers Party (WP), a split precipitated by the party's decision to merge the WP with the Socialist Party. It published the Fighting Worker newspaper. Collection contains letters, memoranda, meeting minutes, party bulletins, financial reports, circulars, and other documents relating to the activities of the Revolutionary Workers League, 1935-1945.
rwleague
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Revolutionary Workers League papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2011.
Historical Note
The Revolutionary Workers League (RWL) was a radical left group in the United States formed in 1935 and active until about 1947. The League was formed by Hugo Oehler in November 1935 following a split from the Workers Party (WP), a split precipitated by the party's decision to merge the WP with the Socialist Party of America. In 1937 the League renounced Trotskyism altogether, although disputes arose within the League as to precisely when Trotsky abandoned Marxism. In the Spanish Civil War the RWL supported the Partido Obrero de Unificaci칩n Marxista de Espa침a (POUM). Oehler and party member Russell Blackwell were present in Spain in July 1937. Blackwell remained in Spain in support of POUM and was eventually arrested by Nationalist forces. The party also published the Fighting Worker newspaper.
Collection Overview
Collection contains letters, memoranda, meeting minutes, party bulletins, financial reports, circulars, and other documents relating to the activities of the Revolutionary Workers League, 1935-1945. Also present are documents relating to the defense of Russell Blackwell, arrested in Spain during the Spanish Civil War.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Oehler, Hugo; Blackwell, Russell; Partido Obrero de Unificaci칩n Marxista de Espa침a.; Revolutionary Workers League; Workers Party of the United States; Socialism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Communism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Labor Unions -- Political Activity -- United States -- History; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, Foreign
Related Material
Workers League for a Revolutionary Party papers, 1945-1946
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Duke University
Communist League of America papers, 1929-1935
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Duke University
Socialist Party records, 1900-1987 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Revolutionary Workers League papers, 1935-1945, (1 box)
  - Clippings, 1938 and undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Internal Communications: 1935 February-June (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Internal Communications: 1935 July-1938 September (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Internal Communications: 1938 October-1939 October (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Internal Communications: 1939 November-1945 February (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Event circulars, 1937-1939 and undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Meeting minutes, 1935 June-1936 March (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Financial papers, 1935, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Negrete Defense, 1938 June-1939 February and undated (Box 1, Folder 9)